A Guide to the Papers of the Allen-Johnson Family 1838-1947
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Allen-Johnson Family Papers 1838-1947
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 48
1 Document Case
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
On loan from Mrs. Patricia Shaw, August 1980
Biographical/Historical Information
The Johnson family is one of the oldest families in New England. The progenitor of this branch of the Johnson family was James Johnson, who was one of eighty men who came to this country with Sir Fernando Gorges in 1621. This group settled on the Isle of Shoals, later to be known as the town of Rye, New Hampshire. His daughter, Mary Johnson, married John Ordiorne, who settled on what is now known as Ordiorne's Point in the town of Newcastle, New Hampshire. A few generations later, Daniel Johnson married Jane Ordiorne furthering the tie between the Johnson and Ordiorne families. Jotham Ordiorne, son of John and Mary Ordiorne, was the first judge of the Superior Court in the Province of New Hampshire.
The Johnson family had a part in every war on the continent, with the exception of the war with Mexico, a war that was waged to obtain more slave territory, and which was not popular in New England. Philip Johnson was with Sir William Pepperel at the capture of Louisburg, C.B. in 1690. Lewis Johnson was with DeWolf at the capture of Quebec from the French. Daniel Johnson was a soldier in the Revolutionary war. Another Johnson was a member of General Ulmer's Regiment in the war of 1812. The brothers, John and Ralph Johnson served in the Civil War. Ralph was killed at the battle of the Wilderness. John served as an officer in the Navy, and was promoted twice for his gallant conduct in action.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists of mostly personal correspondence between the members of the Johnson and Allen families of Maine, who were related by marriage. The letters date from 1838 to 1947. In addition to the correspondence other items included in the collection are photographs of an ice storm, postcard, genealogical information, receipts and accounts. Aside from its insight into the lives of members of the Johnson and Allen families, this collection has some information that may be of interest to someone researching the genealogy of the Johnson and Allen families, as well as the Tracy's of Maine who are also related.
Arrangement
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Organization
The collection is organized into three series: I. Personal Correspondence; II Business Papers; III Miscellaneous.
Series I: Personal Correspondence. This series contains personal correspondence among the Johnson, Allen, and Tracy families between 1838 and 1947.
Series II: Business Papers. This series includes receipts made out to Franklin Johnson in the 1870s and to Henry Tracy in the 1930s. The receipts are for printing, coal, and taxes. Also included are account statements for John A. Johnson for 1859.
Series III: Miscellaneous. This series includes photographs, cards, newspaper clippings (mainly obituaries and historical articles), and a list of births in the Johnson family from 1788 to 1849. Also included are a Knox County Consumer's Sugar Card (for rationing during the war) and "The Maniacs: Kora Temple Shrine Song."
Contents List
- Personal Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1838-1859 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1860-1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1865-1870 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1871-1947 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, not dated (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
- Business Papers
  - Receipts (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Statements of Account (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
- Miscellaneous
  - Photographs and cards (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
  - List of births and deaths, Johnson Family, 1788-1849 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Essay "History of the Flag" (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)